<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: memories | valeriu caraulean]]></title>
  <link href="http://caraulean.com/blog/categories/memories/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://caraulean.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-16T00:28:46+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://caraulean.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Valeriu Caraulean]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nostalgy. My early days as a software developer ...]]></title>
    <link href="http://caraulean.com/blog/2011/04/28/nostalgy-in-my-early-days-as-a-software-developer/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-28T02:03:22+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://caraulean.com/blog/2011/04/28/nostalgy-in-my-early-days-as-a-software-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Something brought up old memories from the days when I’ve been working in Embedded Systems development.</p>

<p><img src="/../../../../../images/2011/dsc00984.jpg" alt="alt screenshot" /></p>

<p>I’m third from the left...</p>

<p>The “big thing” in the back is a Diesel engine stripped from a big ship. Converted to an internal combustion engine working on natural gas and producing 6 Megawatts of Electrical power. Cooling/heating, turbo, oiling, ignition – those are only few subsystems of this complex.</p>

<p>One more picture:</p>

<p><img src="/../../../../../images/2011/dsc00931.jpg" alt="alt screenshot" /></p>

<p>My former employer, <a href="http://rgg.md">Romany Gaz Group</a>, done all the electronics + software. It was a blast to work on. A mix of hardware, microprocessors and software, low level hacking and unforgettable feeling of true Research and Development work:</p>

<ul>
<li>writing in assembler for mythical Motorola 68HC11, an 8-bit microprocessor with a whopping 64 Kb of program memory and less than 1 Kb of RAM. Then come the HC12 with more memory and C compiler.</li>
<li>in-house Real-Time Operational System with multi-tasking support.</li>
<li>“advanced” user interfaces on 20x4 character displays and 5 button keyboards</li>
<li>homebrew communication protocol spawning into few levels of OSI model</li>
<li>tens of sensors and digital signals</li>
<li>tens of output signals, valves, pumps</li>
<li>a SCADA-like PC application for monitoring and control</li>
</ul>


<p>And a fantastic team of talented engineers that tamed the beast. You have to hear it grumble...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
